Just one place... just one place...
tatta hitotsu tatta hitotsu no...
Just one of me... just one of me...
tatta hitori tatta hitori no...
I'm right here.
watashi wa koko
With a chest made of rubble, I can't even breathe.
gareki no mune iki mo dekinai
The rain starts to fall, like a slumbering cry.
furidasu ame nemuru you ni cry
What flower should I decorate myself with
kono sekai o ikinuku no naraba
To stay alive in this world?
donna hana o kazareba ii no?
I want to believe, but still can't manage it...
shinjitai kuse ni shinjirarezu ni
My powerless and pointless self
muryoku de muimi na jibun ga
Still embraces my heart.
soredemo kokoro de idakun da
I can hear a voice calling to me, saying, "Come this way!"
"kocchi e oide" to koe ga kikoeru
A limitless and reckless tomorrow
mugen de mubou na ashita ga
Will still be waiting for me somewhere.
soredemo dokoka de matsu kara
Just one place... just one place...
tatta hitotsu tatta hitotsu no...
Just one of me... just one of me...
tatta hitori tatta hitori no...
I'm right here.
watashi wa koko
（リンデル）
しばしの辛抱じゃ
おとなしく待っておれよ
It won't take long.
Be patient.
How did I get here?
（チセ）
なんで
こんなことになってるんだろう
Elias was telling me about the dragons, and...
確か エリアスに
ドラゴンのことを聞いていて…
Dragons?
（チセ）ドラゴン？
（エリアス）そう ドラゴン
Yes, dragons.
They've been on the move lately.
（エリアス）
最近
活動が活発になっているらしくてね
I've been asked to check it out.
様子見を頼まれた
ここアイスランドには
ドラゴンたちの巣があるんだ
Here, in Iceland, is the dragons' nest.
They're on the verge of extinction, just like us mages.
絶滅寸前なのは
ドラゴンも 僕たち魔法使いも
一緒でね
The handful of surviving breeds have
been rounded up here to be taken care of.
ほんの少し残った種類を
この地で まとめて管理してるのさ
It's remote and scarcely inhabited here,
which makes it a perfect hiding space.
人が少なくて手も入らない ここは
目くらましには
もってこいだからね
Are they vicious?
（チセ）凶暴なんですか？
The majority of them were weeded out long ago.
（エリアス）
大半は大昔に淘汰(とうた)されて
There are more docile ones now.
穏やかな個体が多くなったよ
I see.
そうなんですか
Chise!
（エリアス）チセ！
（チセ）エ… エリアス！
Elias!
フッ…
あやつも なまじ力があるだけに
His half-baked talent makes him cocky.
He hasn't changed much.
油断ばかりするのは変わらんなあ
そら！ もう見えたぞ
See, look over there.
ドラゴンたちの最後の地だ
The last land of the dragons.
（雛竜(ひなりゅう)たち）ん？
Hey, let her go.
おい 放せ
（翼竜）グィ？
Hey!
おい！
そのまま沈む気か？
Does she plan to just keep sinking?
My body feels heavy.
（チセ）
体が… 重い…
（エリアス）
チセ…
Chise.
チセ！
ぷはっ…
ゲホッ ゲホッ
ハア… ハア…
（ネヴィン）おや
Well.
What an unusual guest.
（ネヴィン）珍しいお客だ
You smell like a mage...
魔法使いのような匂いがする
albeit a young one.
しかし まだ柔らかい…
若芽の匂いだね
A sapling.
And you smell of plants,
flowers, and rocks from another place.
それに
ここではない緑や花や石の匂いも
It's a nice scent.
いい匂いだ
His eyes...
（チセ）
このヒト 目が…
His whole body is like a forest of moss, too.
それに 体中 苔(こけ)だらけの森みたい
He's a breed of dragon called an uil.
（リンデル）
それは
ウーイルという種のドラゴンだ
He's both father and the mother to the forest,
bearing vegetation on his decaying body.
森の父にして母
朽ちゆく巨体に緑を宿すものよ
手荒にして すまんな
Apologies for the rough handling.
ドラゴンの国へようこそ
影の茨(ソーン)の娘よ
Welcome to the land of dragons, Daughter of Thorn.
Why me?
（チセ）なんで 私を？
There was commotion among the ariels.
（リンデル）
エアリエルたちが
騒いでおったのでな
They said that Thorn had finally taken an apprentice.
あのソーンが
とうとう弟子を取ったと
For them, rumors spread literally like the wind.
あやつらのうわさは
まさに風のごとしよ
此度(こたび)は素早かったのう
You arrived quite quickly this time around.
いつまで弟子の影に引っ付いておる
When are you going to stop hiding
in your apprentice's shadows, Thorn?
ソーン…
いや エインズワース
Or rather, Ainsworth?
（エリアス）
年寄りのくだらない話が
終わるまでだよ
When the old fogey finishes his bumbling.
It's been 300 years, and you still haven't
stopped toying with people, have you, Echos?
他人をおもちゃにするのは
300年前から変わらないな
白花の歌(エコーズ)
よいのか？ エインズワース
お主の弟子が凍え死ぬぞ
Do you want your apprentice
to freeze to death, Ainsworth?
（チセ）ハア…
I'm... I'm fine.
だ… 大丈夫です
You're absolutely soaked.
（エリアス）まったく…
ずぶぬれになってるじゃないか
影にイラクサ
Nettles in the shadow...
Ring of holly...
ヒイラギの輪
乾いた…
I'm dry.
Th-Thank you.
あ… ありがとうございます
What are you grinning at?
（エリアス）何を にやにやしてる
At this little brat acting like he's all grown up.
ガキが 一丁前に
親のまね事なぞしておるなと
Shut it.
（エリアス）うるさい
（リンデル）フフン
（エリアス）
チセ あいつはリンデル
Chise, that's Lindel.
He's a mage, like me, and caretaker of this dragon's nest.
このドラゴンの巣の管理者で
僕と同じ魔法使いだ
（チセ）管理者？
Caretaker?
（エリアス）
魔法で ドラゴンの国を
普通の人間から隠す役目をしてる
His duty is to keep the land of dragons
hidden from the sight of ordinary humans.
Hence, "caretaker."
だから 管理者さ
Despite his appearance, he's a
mischievous senior, even more ancient than I am,
こんな形(なり)でも 僕より ずっと年上の
いたずらジジイだから
気をつけてね
so be careful around him.
（リンデル）貴様…
How dare you...
（雛竜Ａ）
ねえねえ お話 終わった？
Hey, hey!
Are you done talking?
（雛竜Ｂ）遊ぼ！
Let's play.
（雛竜たち）遊ぼ！ 遊ぼ！
（チセ）うわっ…
Let's play! Let's play!
Come on.
（リンデル）
フフッ
そいつらはドラゴンの雛だよ
Those are dragon hatchlings.
Let's play.
Let's play!
The one with wings is a gwee.
翼があるのが グィーで
足元のが ベァナ
Please?
Come on!
The one by your feet is a beana.
Come on, let's play!
The slow-moving one is an uil.
動きのゆっくりしたものは
ウーイルだ
まあ わしが勝手に
そう呼んでいるだけだがな
Granted, that's just what I call them personally.
Let's play!
Come on!
Hey, are you listening?
Lindel.
（エリアス）リンデル
（リンデル）ん？
Let's play!
Tell me, has there been any trouble lately?
（エリアス）
ここ最近 何か問題はなかったか
聞かせてくれ
ハア…
またぞろ 連中 気にしだしたか
They're making a fuss again, are they?
Food has been scarce this year.
今年は餌が少なくて
遠出をするドラゴンが多くてな
A number of the dragons have been traveling far.
（雛竜たち）
ねえねえ！ 遊ぼうよ
聞いてよ〜
（雛竜たち）遊ぼ！
Chise, would you mind playing with them for me?
（リンデル）
チセ そやつらと
遊んでやってもらえるかの
何して遊ぶ？
What should we do?
あそこ あそこ！
Over there.
Let's jump off and practice gliding toward the pond.
あの上から飛び降りて
お池 目指して 滑空の練習！
今の人間て飛べるんでしょ？
Humans can fly these days, right?
Er, that might be hard without having my
bones and muscles modified at the genetic level.
（チセ）
それは 骨格と筋肉を
遺伝子レベルで改造しなきゃ
ちょ〜っと難しいかな
Yay!
わ〜い！ わ〜い！
せっかく乾いたのに…
And now I'm wet again.
（雛竜たち）
ねえねえ あれできる？
かっこよかった？
Hey, can we try that?
That was awesome!
（雛竜Ａ）グィ〜
（チセ）
翼があるってことは飛べるのかな
He has wings, so I guess he must be able to fly.
He's all tattered, though.
でも ぼろぼろ…
（ネヴィン）
ドラゴンを見るのは初めてかい？
Have you never seen a dragon before?
（チセ）
あ… すっ すみません 勝手に
S-Sorry, I didn't mean to...
I didn't mean it like that.
（ネヴィン）
ああ… そういう意味で
言ったわけではないよ
（雛竜Ａ）
ネヴィンのおじちゃん 起きた！
Uncle Nevin's awake.
（ネヴィン）
私は もうすぐ還(かえ)る身だから
It's won't be long before I return home.
転がる雛を見ているほうが
楽しいんじゃないかとね
I'd supposed you would prefer to
watch over the rollicking young instead.
It's almost his time.
ネヴィンのおじちゃん
もうそろそろだね
His time?
Uncle Nevin's turning into a tree soon.
ネヴィンのおじちゃんね
もうすぐ樹(き)になるの！
Yup.
All the uils do.
（雛竜Ｃ）
ウーイルたちは
みんな そうだよ
They turn into excellent trees and pasture.
とってもいい樹や
草になるの
When you say "return"...
（チセ）“還る”って…
What do you mean?
どういう…
We're going to turn into trees and
moss and boulders when we die, too.
僕らも 死んだら樹になったり
苔になったり 岩になるんだよ
Right?
When you die?
（チセ）“死んだら”って…
We don't fear death the way you humans do.
（ネヴィン）
私たちは 人間のように
死ぬことを恐れない
We live our lives to the fullest,
so that we're never left with regrets.
いつだって悔いのないよう
生きられるだけ生きるものだから
Doesn't it hurt?
（チセ）痛く… ないですか？
You're a kind-hearted child.
（ネヴィン）お前は優しい子供だね
We understand that what is given to us is the same
私たちは 訪れるそれが
この星の生き物全てに
等しく与えられるものだと
as what is given to all who live on this planet.
識(し)っているんだ
Whether that's the joy or the pain of living,
or the sadness or loneliness of dying.
生きることの苦痛も 楽しさも
死ぬことの寂しさも 悲しさも
それに 私は十分 生きた
Besides, I've lived for more than enough time.
For a long, long time, even for a dragon.
ドラゴンにとっても長い…
永い年月をね
Life will be handed down to the next generation.
次の命は次の世代が引き継ぐ
You have no reason to grieve.
君が悲しむ必要はない
（チセ）
違う…
No.
悲しんでなんかいない
I'm not grieving.
できない
I can't.
そんな…
It's really...
（ネヴィン）
生きるものが
死者を羨むものじゃない
The living shouldn't envy the dead.
飛べない君が飛ばなくてよかった
You cannot fly, so it's fortunate that you didn't.
He wouldn't have known who to take
as his apprentice if he hadn't met you.
君に会えなかったら
彼は誰を弟子にしていいのか
分からなかっただろうからね
Were you going through my memories?
（チセ）もしかして 私の記憶を…
（ネヴィン）
人間には ぶしつけだった
すまない
That was a disrespectful thing to do to a human.
I'm sorry.
I believe I ought to let you experience the
joy of true flight, as you cannot fly yourself.
飛べない君には
本当に飛ぶ楽しさを
教えたほうがよさそうだ
I don't have the strength to fly anymore,
今の私に飛ぶ力はないけれど…
（雛竜たち）わあ〜！
but I can show you the sky I see in my mind.
（ネヴィン）
私の心にある空は
見せることができる
Behold.
それを見せよう
Looks like Nevin is having his
final dream, along with Chise.
（リンデル）
ネヴィンが
最期の夢を見ておるようじゃ
チセと共に
（エリアス）
今のドラゴンは
代替わりが激しくなってきたし
A lot of dragons are passing the torch lately.
I suppose he's the last of the old dragons.
あれが最後の旧(ふる)いドラゴンかな
（リンデル）
ドラゴンも魔法も 一緒よな
It's the same for dragons as it is for magic, isn't it?
人間が増え
時代を経る度 追われていく
We're being pushed aside by the changing
times and the growing number of humans.
（エリアス）
チセが魔法使いになれば
最後の世代とも言われかねないね
If Chise becomes a mage,
she may very well be of the last generation.
Does that bother you?
（リンデル）気がかりかの？
Chise's power is flowing into Nevin.
（リンデル）
チセの魔力が
ネヴィンに流れ込んでおる
ネヴィンには
良き力添えになるだろうが…
She'll be a great help to Nevin,
夜の愛し仔(スレイ･ベガ)の過ぎた魔力は
ときに その者自身を傷つける
but a Sleigh Beggy's overwhelming
power, at times, hurts its wielder.
She doesn't know how to hold back yet.
（エリアス）
あの子は まだ加減を知らないんだ
Isn't it your job to teach her?
それを教えるのが
お前の役目じゃろう
このまま 思うに任せていれば
あの子の体は３年ともたんぞ
She won't last three years unless you stop her.
I know.
（エリアス）分かってる
Don't let her out of your sight.
（リンデル）目を離すでないぞ
There are countless people who want a Sleigh Beggy.
スレイ･ベガを欲する輩(やから)は
ごまんといる
The rumors these days aren't encouraging.
このところ
良くないうわさも聞くからの
（エリアス）
せっかく手に入れたものだもの
そう簡単に手放しはしないよ
She wasn't easy to obtain.
I won't let her go that easily.
ハア…
I hope she grows up safely...
無事 育てばいいのだがの
That Sleigh Beggy.
あのスレイ･ベガ…
Our kind abandoned the skies.
（ネヴィン）
我々の一族は空を捨てたが
But it was always our fate to dwell beneath it.
いつだって
この空の下で生きてゆく定めだ
その名にある鳥のように
Your name has the character for "bird" within it.
You must also fly beneath this sky, in order to live.
君も 生きるために
この空の下を飛びなさい
（チセ）生きるために…
In order to live?
Fly?
飛ぶ…
In order to live...
（チセ）
生きるために…
樹が…
It's a tree.
Thank you.
（ネヴィン）ありがとう
Because you were here,
I spent my last moments in flight.
君が来てくれたおかげで 最期に…
飛べた
I didn't do anything.
私は何も…
A little while ago,
Lindel planted a small seed in my body.
（ネヴィン）少し前に
リンデルが
小さな種を体に植えてくれた
It'll produce beautiful white flowers, I'm told.
白い…
きれいな花が咲くらしい
You're a mage, are you not?
君は魔法使いだろう？
You'll need a wand, someday.
いつか杖(つえ)が必要になるだろうから
Make one out of my branches.
私の枝から作るとよい
Good night, little mage.
おやすみ 小さな魔法使い
おじちゃん すごいね！
Uncle was awesome.
Wasn't he?
僕も
こんな大きな樹になれるかなあ
I hope I can become a huge tree, too.
Welcome back, Chise.
（エリアス）おかえり チセ
Was it beautiful in Nevin's sky?
ネヴィンの空は
きれいだったかい？
It was very beautiful.
とても… きれいでした
（エリアス）珍しいものを見れたな
That was a rare thing you got to witness.
Not many get to witness a dragon return to the earth.
ドラゴンが地に還るのを見る機会は
とても少ないんだ
Lindenbaum.
リンデンバウムだ
白いきれいな花が咲いてる
Its beautiful white flowers are in bloom.
There's not a single reason to be sad, Chise.
（リンデル）
悲しむ必要など
ひとかけらもないぞ チセ
This is the work of nature.
これは摂理よ
The dragons all spend enormous
time strengthening their minds,
はるか昔から
ドラゴンたちが育んできた精神の末
and in the end, are at peace with
becoming seedbeds for other life.
ドラゴンたちは 皆 穏やかに
ほかの生物の苗床になるのだから
はい
Okay.
（エリアス）必要になったら
Like Nevin said,
we'll return for a branch to use for your
wand, once it's time for you to have one.
ネヴィンの言ったとおり
杖に使う枝をもらいに来よう
Our business here is done for now.
とりあえず
今回の件は終わったからね
Let's head home.
そろそろ帰ろう
What? Leaving so soon?
（リンデル）
なんじゃ もう帰るのか？
This isn't the only matter I've had shoved at me.
（エリアス）
ほかにも
押しつけられた用件があるんだよ
You could just bail on it.
（リンデル）すっぽかせばいいのに
You're surprisingly proper, aren't you?
案外 真面目じゃの ぬしも
Shut up.
（エリアス）ほっとけ
This is nature...
（チセ）
これが自然か…
（エリアス）チセ 行くよ
Let's go, Chise.
I'm not sad.
（チセ）
悲しくは… ない
He was just like a stranger who
happened to show me some kindness.
通りすがりに優しくしてもらった
だけのようなヒトだったし
なんか めまいがする…
My head's spinning.
Is it because of the flight?
空 飛んだ… せいかな…
でも やっぱり…
But still,
I can't help but be a little envious
あの穏やかな還り方は
of the peaceful way he passed.
少し…
羨ましい
To keep the seeds I tie to this branch
eda ni musubu mi ga jukusu mae ni
From falling before they ripen
ochite shimawanu you
I bloom again in profusion, painfully
kurushii hodo ni mata sakimidareru
To connect myself to tomorrow.
asa e tsunagu you
Even as they're born again
nando kurikaeshi
And again,
kurikaeshi umaretemo
I'll always show them
itsumo atarashii
A brand new sky.
sora o misete ageyou
I'll pen a story that no one,
daremo mada daremo
No one has ever written.
kaitenai monogatari
On a map so white, pure white,
shiroi masshiroi
I'll draw it out, singing it aloud.
chizu ni kaite utaou
（チセ）
トンネルを抜けると
そこは猫の国だった
Past the tunnel was a nation of cats.
悲しみの沈む地で
少女は己の残酷な宿命を知る
There, in a land drowning in sadness,
the girl learns of her own cruel duty.
Please, help us. Help me.
（ミナ）
お願い このヒトを… 私を…